{"tossups": [{"question": "This poet of \"Birches\" wrote a poem in which \"my little horse must think it queer\" to stop in the title place, and said \"I have promises to keep, / And miles to go before I sleep\" in (*) \"Stopping by Woods on a Snowy Evening.\" \"Two roads diverged in a yellow wood\" in another poem by this American poet. For ten points, name this poet of \"Fire and Ice\" and \"The Road Not Taken.\"", "answer": "Robert Lee Frost", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This family led the German Confederation until they lost the Seven Weeks War. A member of this family lost control of Silesia to Frederick the Great. Charles II of Spain had this inbred family's namesake (*) jawline. Maria Theresa was a member of, for ten points, what Austrian family that controlled Spain and the Holy Roman Empire?", "answer": "Habsburg (accept Hapsburg; accept House of Lorraine)", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Okazaki fragments help replicate this molecule's lagging strand with polymerase after the strand is unzipped by helicase. This molecule consists of (*) nucleotides formed from thymine, adenine, guanine, and cytosine. James Watson and Francis Crick discovered the double helix structure of, for ten points, what biomolecule that codes genetic information within genes?", "answer": "DNA (accept deoxyribonucleic acid)", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A caldera in this location formed after a series of eruptions at Mesa Falls and Huckleberry Ridge, and contains a supervolcano named after this North American park. This national park contains a (*) geyser known for a very predictable eruption pattern. For ten points, name this protected area in Wyoming whose Old Faithful helped establish it as America's first national park.", "answer": "Yellowstone National Park", "subcategory": "Geography American", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "The \"Augurs\" of this time period is the first dance in a work choreographed by Vaslav Nijinsky. The arrival of this period inspires ritual dancing in an Igor Stravinsky ballet that triggered riots in 1913 Paris. (*) Vivaldi included a \"barking dog\" in a violin concerto named for this period. For ten points, name this first of Vivaldi's Four Seasons, which precedes the movement \"Summer.\"", "answer": "spring (accept La primavera; accept The Rite of Spring)", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A series of reactions named for two of these objects describes the fusion of hydrogen into helium. This particle is the heavier product of beta-minus decay. This particle is made up of two up quarks and one down quark, and the (*) number of these particles in an atom equals the atomic number of its element. For ten points, name this particle that is found in the nucleus with neutrons.", "answer": "proton", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In this play, Lennox and a nobleman from Fife enter Inverness Castle, breaking the protagonist's focus on a murder. This play's title murderer becomes the Thane of Glamis and (*) Cawdor, in accordance with a prophecy given by three witches to him and Banquo, and takes the throne after killing King Duncan. For ten points, name this \"Scottish play\" by William Shakespeare.", "answer": "The Tragedy of Macbeth", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This government body resolved the Yazoo land scandal and determined in 1803 that, even though John Adams erred in not delivering a commission, the (*) Judiciary Act in question was unconstitutional. This body was led for over thirty years by John Marshall, who helped decide the Marbury v. Madison case. For ten points, name this group of nine justices, the highest court in the United States.", "answer": "United States Supreme Court (accept Supreme Court of the United States or SCOTUS)", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In the Brazilian release of this film, Boi Cha \u0301 replaces Peter Moosebridge as a newscaster. In this film, Manchas, a mob boss's limo driver, is attacked by a savage florist, and pastry chef Gideon Grey helps reveal (*) Bellwether's plot, which uses \"night howlers\" to bring out the feral side of predators like fox Nick Wilde. For ten points, name this 2016 Disney film in which rabbit Officer Judy Hopps fights crime in the title animal city.", "answer": "Zootopia (accept Zootropolis)", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "In Sikhism, a Dastar protects this substance, which is called Kesh and tended with a Kangha, two of the Five K's. Payot are a variety of this substance worn in Orthodox Judaism, and some Muslims cover this substance with a (*) hijab. Samson derived his strength from this substance, and became weak when Delilah cut it. For ten points, name this substance that grows out of human heads and faces.", "answer": "human hair", "subcategory": "Religion Other", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "In August 2016, the holder of this position suggested that, after two surgeries, his country's Parliament should amend the Imperial Household Act and allow him to retire. The 1946 (*) Humanity Declaration denied the godhood of people with this title. For ten points, name this position held by Akihito since the 1989 death of his father, Hirohito, the leader of an east Asian nation.", "answer": "Emperor of Japan (accept Tenno)", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This location includes Homey Airport near Groom Lake, where Lockheed established \"the Ranch\" for engineers working on the U-2 within Nellis Air Force Range. The existence of this facility was admitted in 2013 by the (*) CIA. For ten points, name this Nevada facility where the US Air Force probably tests experimental aircraft and probably doesn't hold the alien remains from Roswell, New Mexico.", "answer": "Area 51 (prompt on \"Homey Airport,\" \"Groom Lake,\" or \"Nellis Air Force Range (or Base)\" before they are read)", "subcategory": "Geography American", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "A popular method for solving systems of linear equations works one of these objects into reduced \"row-echelon form.\" If one of these objects is (*) square, its trace is simply the sum of values along a diagonal, and these mathematical arrangements have an inverse if and only if their determinant is not zero. For ten points, name these rectangular arrays of numbers, arranged in columns and rows.", "answer": "matrix (accept matrices)", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Thomas Midgley used this element to boost octane rating and stop engine knocking, but in the 1970s, the United States banned the use of this element as a fuel additive. Exposure to this element increases the risk of neurological problems, especially in (*) children; a recent case of such exposure is ongoing in Flint, Michigan. For ten points, name this toxic element found in old paint and pipes, whose chemical symbol is Pb.", "answer": "lead (accept Pb before it is read)", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "At the beginning of this novel, the captain of the Demeter writes about the disappearance of the entire crew and seeing a large dog-like creature. Instead of marrying her, Quincey Morris and Dr Seward help kill (*) Lucy Westenra in this novel. Jonathan Harker enlists the help of Abraham Van Helsing in this novel. For ten points, name this novel by Bram Stoker about a Transylvanian vampire.", "answer": "Dracula", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This man painted five subjects modeled on Spanish prostitutes and African masks in Les Demoiselles d'Avignon. In a mural-sized painting inspired by the (*) Spanish Civil War, this artist painted a bull standing over a screaming mother under an exploding black-and-white light bulb. For ten points, name this painter of Guernica, who helped found the Cubist movement.", "answer": "Pablo Ruiz y Picasso", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This figure's followers were said to devour raw flesh, usually after tearing a bull apart with their bare hands. Pentheus was similarly torn apart by the maenads, this god's crazed female worshipers. This god's mortal mother, (*) Semele, died of seeing the full glory of Zeus, who then sewed this god into his thigh. For ten points, name this \"twice-born\" Greek god of theater, fertility, and wine.", "answer": "Dionysus (accept Bacchus)", "subcategory": "Mythology Greco-Roman", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "This leader ended an invasion shortly after the head of his brother, Hasdrubal, was thrown into his camp. This man ravaged the Italian countryside for over a decade but was defeated at (*) Zama by Scipio Africanus, ending the Second Punic War. For ten points, name this Carthaginian general who led a military force, including elephants, over the Alps.", "answer": "Hannibal Barca", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A storm on this planet, named Oval BA, formed from the merger of three small white storms in 2000. The solar-powered Juno probe began orbiting this planet in 2016. In 1994, Comet (*) Shoemaker-Levy 9 collided with this planet, providing evidence for its role as the \"vacuum cleaner\" of the Solar System. A centuries-old storm called the \"Great Red Spot\" rages on, for ten points, what largest planet in the Solar System?", "answer": "Jupiter", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In this work, a ship's crew is cursed after they kill cattle belonging to Helios in an effort to get past a whirlpool, and Laertes's daughter-in-law repeatedly weaves and unravels a burial shroud. (*) Penelope is reunited with her husband in this epic poem after he gets past Scylla, Charybdis, and sirens to return to Ithaca. For ten points, name this epic poem by Homer in which a namesake king returns home after the Trojan War.", "answer": "The Odyssey \ufffc", "subcategory": "Classical Literature", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": []}